<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>TGM Guide</title>
 <link href="https://tgmguide.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://tgmguide.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2020-10-01T09:05:41+02:00</updated>
 <id>https://tgmguide.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>sinefuse</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Setting up an emulator to play TGM and TAP</title>
   <link href="https://tgmguide.github.io/2020/05/03/setting-up-an-emulator/"/>
   <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://tgmguide.github.io/2020/05/03/setting-up-an-emulator</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome! This guide will teach you how to set up an emulator to play TGM and TAP.
For a TL;DR, it’s recommend for you to check out the Introductory guide, available over the sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we will do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download Shmupmametgm, the emulator of choice for easy setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install and set up Shmupmametgm properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configure inputs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable Free Play so we don’t have to feed our game “coins”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, let us get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, you will have to download Shmupmametgm, the download link for that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MaryHal/shmupmametgm/releases/download/v2.1/shmupmametgm_windows_2.1.zip&quot;&gt;right here.&lt;/a&gt; Once you have it downloaded, head over to the folder where you downloaded it to. We will now unzip the archive, and for convenience’s sake, we will unzip it to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\MAMETGM\&lt;/code&gt; (You can unzip this wherever you like, of course. We will just use this directory for simplicity’s sake). To do this, right click the archive named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shmupmametgm_windows_2.1.zip&lt;/code&gt; and click on “Extract all” as shown in the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/emusetup/ExtractAll.png&quot; alt=&quot;Extract All&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, paste in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\MAMETGM\&lt;/code&gt; into the textbox you see in the window that came up, check “Show extracted files when complete” and click on “Extract”. After this, the folder with the emulator itself should be there, almost ready to go. One thing you will have to do is create a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;roms&lt;/code&gt; folder in the directory that just opened. In here, you put all of your legally obtained ROM images, which should still be inside their .zip files. You zip them after all to make sure that MAME can read them. Your folder should look a bit like this now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/emusetup/FolderOverview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Folder Overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re almost done at this point. There’s additional steps you can take to make the games look better! What you want to do is hold your SHIFT key, right click in an empty space in your explorer window, and go on “Open PowerShell window here”. Paste the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.\mametgm64.exe -cc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this does is create a file called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mame.ini&lt;/code&gt;. This file has plethora of options you can change to make your game look as crispy as possible, as without the changes we are about to do, it’ll look like a big ‘ol blurry mess. We don’t like blurry messes, so let’s go ahead and open &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mame.ini&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you need to do now, once notepad has opened, is hold your CONTROL key and press F (for once, not to pay respects). A “search” dialog will open up. You want to type in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt;, and it should look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/emusetup/NotepadSearch.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notepad Search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should find a setting that says &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;filter 1&lt;/code&gt;. We change the 1 to a 0, which disables the blurring of the individual pixels in-game (menus will still look blurry), keeping them sharp and crispy - not to mention, it also gets closer to looking like the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to play windowed, you need to change 2 more settings inside the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mame.ini&lt;/code&gt; file, which are &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;window&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;resolution&lt;/code&gt;. You search for them like you searched for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; earlier (press CONTROL + F), you might have to change the search direction however to make sure Notepad can find what we are looking for. You want to change &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;window&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;resolution&lt;/code&gt; to a multiple of 320x240, as that is the resolution the games run. For your convenience, here is a list of perfectly scaled resolutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;320x240&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;640x480&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;960x720 - Recommended for monitors with 1366x768 as resolution, mainly older laptops.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1280x960 - Recommended for 1080p monitors, but you can try a lower resolution first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1600x1200 - Works for 1440p monitors, but you might be more comfortable with a lower resolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
 While you can play in fullscreen of course, take note that on a monitor at 1366x768 resolution, fullscreen will look weird. 720p, 1080p, 1440p and above are generally fine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re finally ready to fire up the emulator! Launch mametgm64.exe and you’ll be greeted with a selection of games. You can choose with the ARROW KEYS and the ENTER key. There’s only 2 games that you should launch from here, which are “TGM” and “TGM2P”, the latter of which is also known as “TAP”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you start a game, a window will pop up - just type “OK” on your keyboard and the game will boot. From here, you need to press your TAB key to open up a configuration menu. From here, using the ARROW KEYS and ENTER, you can enter the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Input (General)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Input (this Game)&lt;/code&gt; submenus and change your inputs how you’d like them, by going to whatever button you want to change, pressing ENTER once and then the key you’d like to use for that button. Once you’re done with setting them up in a specific way, you can press ESCAPE to exit out of the submenu and go into the other, or close the menu altogether. Do make sure to unbind (or re-bind) the Player 2 buttons to avoid input conflicts. To unbind a button, press enter to have it wait for what key you want to assign to the button, and press ESCAPE. Also, in case you are interested, here’s how the guide’s main maintainer, sinefuse, has their inputs set up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1 Player Start - Kbd 1
P1 Up          - W
P1 Down        - S
P1 Left        - A
P1 Right       - D
P1 Button 1    - J
P1 Button 2    - K
P1 Button 3    - L
All P2 buttons - Unbinded
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you want to have your inputs that way is your own decision, of course, but the layout sinefuse uses is somewhat like an arcade setup, with movement inputs on the left and rotation inputs on the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this one is kind of important to avoid tedium: you will also see a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Service Menu&lt;/code&gt; key, which should be mapped to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;F2&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Keep it that way&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s an important key, and once you’ve exited out of the menu we opened to change our controls, that’s precisely the key we will press to open up the &lt;strong&gt;Test Menu&lt;/strong&gt;. We want to enable Free Play in the games so we don’t have to always “throw in coins” into the emulator to play a round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In TGM, you want to go down to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;7. CONFIGURATION&lt;/code&gt;, enter it, enter the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1. SYSTEM&lt;/code&gt; setting and then change the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1. COIN&lt;/code&gt; setting to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;FREE PLAY&lt;/code&gt;. It should look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/emusetup/FreePlayTGM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Free Play on TGM&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you did that, you can navigate to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;5. EXIT&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;4. SAVE &amp;amp; EXIT&lt;/code&gt;. It will save the settings, and then you can navigate to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;9. EXIT&lt;/code&gt; and start playing the game by pressing the 1 Player Start key a few times!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For TAP, you want to go to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Game Setting&lt;/code&gt; enter that, then down to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Coin Mode&lt;/code&gt; and press left once to switch to Free Play. It should look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/emusetup/FreePlayTAP.png&quot; alt=&quot;Free Play on TAP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/code&gt; and then to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Exit (Reset)&lt;/code&gt;. Now you can start playing by just pressing your 1 Player Start key a bunch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with that, your emulator is properly set up and ready to go. Enjoy playing TGM!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Setting up Texmaster2009</title>
   <link href="https://tgmguide.github.io/2020/05/02/setting-up-texmaster/"/>
   <updated>2020-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://tgmguide.github.io/2020/05/02/setting-up-texmaster</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This guide will tell you how to get Texmaster2009 running.
Normally, we’d tell you to check out the introductory guide, but unfortunately, we haven’t gotten around to updating the TL;DR for it juuust yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the steps we’re taking on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Downloading Texmaster2009-5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seting up Texmaster properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OPTIONAL: Seting up “Termino Velocity”, a custom theme&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;downloading-texmaster2009-5&quot;&gt;Downloading Texmaster2009-5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing you need is Texmaster itself, of course. The link for that can be &lt;a href=&quot;http://mindflyer.net/tetris/texmaster/Texmaster2009-5.7z&quot;&gt;Right about here.&lt;/a&gt; You’ll need 7-Zip to unpack the archive. If you don’t have it yet, use your mighty Google powers and find any mirror to download it from. (TODO link 7-Zip website) Just unzip it anywhere and you will end up with a folder named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Texmaster2009&lt;/code&gt;. Enter that folder - You should see something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/texysetup/rootfolder.png&quot; alt=&quot;Texmaster folder, fully extracted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here on out, this place will be referred to as the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; folder in the guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, Texmaster is already ready to go, albeit with a bit of a cramped layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Assuming you have a QWERTY keyboard:
P1 Up          - S
P1 Down        - X
P1 Left        - Z
P1 Right       - C
P1 Button 1    - N
P1 Button 2    - M
P1 Button 3    - ,
P1 Button 4    - Spacebar
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-texmaster-properly&quot;&gt;Setting up Texmaster properly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, of course, we can remedy this, thanks to the wonderful &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Texmaster2009.ini&lt;/code&gt; file we can see in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; folder. Open it up in a text editor of your choice - if you don’t have one yet, we recommend you to give Notepad++ a try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, once in here, there’s a bunch of variables you can change. In the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;[VIDEO]&lt;/code&gt; settings, I recommend you to only change the resolution and whether you want to use fullscreen or not. The other options are a bit more advanced and don’t really matter anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
 Take note that if you want to change the resolution, you should always work with whole numbers, multiplying the base resolution of &lt;b&gt;320x240&lt;/b&gt;! Using any other resolution will make your game look very weird. For example, sinefuse, the guide maintainer, uses 1280x960 (which is 4 times the base resolution), so they've set the width to 1280 and the height to 960.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The part that’s more important to us is the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;[KEYBOARD]&lt;/code&gt; settings, which you can find when scrolling down a bit. This only applies if you do not want to use the base key layout. Go ahead and change the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;player1&lt;/code&gt; variable into a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;5&lt;/code&gt;. This will allow us to set the correct keys by reading from the other variables labled &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;key_type5&lt;/code&gt; right below that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, unfortunately, unlike the example in the .ini file tells you to do, you can’t just put the actual keys you want to use in there and have it work. What you need to do is enter specific numbers which correspond to a certain key. As for which number you have to type in for the individual keys, you will have to go into your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;html&lt;/code&gt; folder which you can find when you have the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; folder open. From there, open &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;key.html&lt;/code&gt;, and there you will have a handy list of which numbers correspond to which keys. Use the search function by pressing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CTRL+F&lt;/code&gt;, type in a key, and you should be able to find the corresponding number quite quickly. Now it’s just a matter of putting those numbers into the specific variables. Here is how the guide maintainer has his set up, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;key_type5_up = 119
key_type5_down = 115
key_type5_left = 97
key_type5_right = 100
key_type5_a = 106
key_type5_b = 107
key_type5_c = 108
key_type5_d = 32
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will result in a layout that uses A and D to go left/right, W for a sonic drop, S for a hard drop, JKL for rotations and the space bar for hold. Basically, it shifts the default layout up by one key row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, once this is all done, you can save your .ini file, as we are pretty much done here. Now is the time where we head into the actual game itself to do things!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re first opening the game, you’re greeted with a nice splash screen and a logo. Press your first rotation key (M in the default key layout) to go into the profile selection menu, and create a new profile. Scroll through the letters with your navigation keys and set your name for the profile. After that, select your profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you’re greeted with whether you want to play in Classic or World mode. Classic is how the TGM games have usually worked, with a rotation system normally known as Arika Rotation System, or ARS for short, where as World mode is used by current-gen Tetris games such as Puyo Puyo Tetris or Tetris Effect, known as Super Rotation System or SRS. However, the implementation for World mode isn’t the best… a lot of things don’t work. We’d highly recommend playing in Classic mode anyways, as it’s more true to the TGM feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here, now you can select any of the modes. Here’s what each mode corresponds to from the real games:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;NOVICE     = Normal mode from TGM2
NORMAL     = TGM1
ADVANCE    = TGM+ mode from TAP
SPECIAL    = Master mode from TGM2
SUDDEN     = T.A. Death mode from TAP
DOUBLES    = Doubles mode from TGM2
SPECIAL Ti = Master mode from Ti
SUDDEN Ti  = Shirase mode from Ti
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the function keys (F1 - F12) All do different things. Here’s what they each do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;F1  - Fast Forward
F2  - Speeds up menus, for some reason...
F3  - Check best section times
F4  - No function
F5  - Screenshot
F6  - Replay viewer
F7  - Sound test
F8  - Change playfield view (Recommended for custom themes!)
F9  - No function
F10 - Show FPS, speed and CPU usage
F11 - Instantly stop game and go back to title screen
F12 - Stop playing current BGM
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with that, you’re pretty much set to go, unless you want to install a custom theme, in which case, read on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seting-up-termino-velocity-a-custom-theme&quot;&gt;Seting up “Termino Velocity”, a custom theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, this game has custom themes. This one, Termino Velocity, is praised by many players to be among the best Texmaster themes ever created. Unfortunately, Digital, the creator of the theme, has been inactive for a long time and the theme ended up being ported painstakingly to the newest Texmaster version by sinefuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you want to install Termino Velocity, which looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/texysetup/terminopreview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Preview of Termino Velocity&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you’re in the right place. It’s quite easy, too: Download &lt;a href=&quot;/public/files/Termino Velocity.7z&quot;&gt;this archive.&lt;/a&gt; Open it and you will find a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; folder. Replace the current &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; folder inside your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; folder of your Texmaster install with the one inside the archive. If you did it correctly, your game should now look like the preview further up. All you need to do now is press F8 to properly align the playfield and you’re done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
 Take note that you will have to press F8 every time you restart the game to properly align the playfield. Texmaster does not save that setting when you close the game.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now go out there and play some Tetris! Feel free to share this guide if it helped you!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Content soon(tm)</title>
   <link href="https://tgmguide.github.io/2020/04/03/WIP/"/>
   <updated>2020-04-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://tgmguide.github.io/2020/04/03/WIP</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned, I’m working on things here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
